# RAFAEL ANDRÉS CAMACHO DEJAY

Date of birth: 31st January 1988 | Venezuelan with residency in Belgium Wijngaardlaan 17, 3001 Heverlee, Belgium | camachodejay@yahoo.com | mobile: +32 493 12 14 48

# SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

7+ years of research experience focusing on advanced microscopy methods and software development. I have been involved in highly interdisciplinary teams, working within the fields of physics, chemistry and biology. I enjoy developing software for image processing and data analytics/visualization. I have built excellent communication skills by presenting complex ideas to broad audiences in international conferences, and group meetings.

## Professional Experience

#### POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER | KU LEUVEN | November 2014 - present

- Design & development of a microscope for 3D super-resolution imaging:
  - + CAD based design of mechanical components.
  - + Software for automated hardware control (Java Micromanager).
- Study of bacterial growth, survival and death by antibiotics using microscopy methods and image analysis software for shape recognition and classification.
  - + Image segmentation/binarization.
  - + Shape descriptors and machine learning for discrimination and classification (MATLAB).
- Simulations of physical systems.
  - + Light absorption and energy transfer. Monte Carlo based methods.
  - + Synthetic image generation fluorescence images, EMCCD, scCMOS.
  - + Particle diffusion and localization.
- Development of software tools for:
  - + Next-generation DNA sequencing e.g. clustering methods.
  - + Single molecule detection/tracking e.g. generalized likelihood ratio test.
  - + Intensity traces –e.g. change point detection via Bayes hypothesis testing, or nonlinear filtering methods.
  - + Super-resolution imaging e.g. FFT, phasors, and image registration.
- Project management and supervision of bachelor, master and PhD students.
- Instructor and organizer of a programming course for young researchers.
- Successful grants: 3-year postdoctoral fellowship (Research Foundation Flanders); 1-year fellowship (Internal funds KU Leuven).

#### POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER | LUND UNIVERSITY | July 2014 - October 2014

- Detection of protein aggregation related to Alzheimer's disease FRET by fluorescence resonance energy transfer imaging.
  - + In charge of project management and establishing long lasting collaborations with researches within live sciences.

#### PHD CANDIDATE & RESEARCHER | LUND UNIVERSITY | May 2010 - June 2014

- Construction of a polarization sensitive fluorescence microscope with single molecule precision.
  - + Hardware prototyping and software integration (LabView/MATLAB)
- Design of graphical user interfaces for data acquisition and analysis.
  - + Basic parallel computing for image analysis (Python).
- Training in value creation and patent application for life sciences.
- Single molecule spectroscopy and imaging methods for the study of material with potential use in nano and molecular electronics.
- Nominated to the Fabian Gyllenbergs prize.

### **EDUCATION**

#### PhD in the subject of Chemistry | Lund University, Sweden | 2014

• Specialization in Chemical Physics and single molecule spectroscopy.

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN CHEMISTRY < Licenciado en Química > | SIMÓN BOLÍVAR UNIVERSITY, VENEZUELA | 2010

- Graduated with cum laude distinction.
- Honourable mention on Final Project.

# SKILLS AND TRAINING

#### PROGRAMMING

- Data handling and processing using MATLAB and Python.
- Familiar with OpenCV, Magick++, and other image processing libraries.
- Moderate experience with C++.
- Automated hardware control using LabVIEW, Micromanager, and Java.
- Object-oriented programming and Model-View-Controller architecture.

#### GitHub and Bitbucket username: CamachoDejay.

#### ENGINEERING & DESIGN

- Strong background in Physics, Chemistry and Mathematics.
- Optical and fluorescence microscopy and super-resolution imaging, e.g. FRET, Light-Sheet, Two-Photon, STORM, SOFI, etc.
- Hands-on experience with state-of-the-art microscopy equipment from Nikon, Olympus, Zeiss and Leica.
- Construction of home-build microscopy and spectroscopy setups.
- Characterization of materials at the nano-scale.
- Experimental skills with bio-organisms, chemicals and lab equipment.
- Moderate experience in 3D Computer-Aided Design (CAD).

#### LANGUAGES

- Spanish: Native
- French: Intermediate and improving
- English: Excellent
- Swedish: Elementary

# OTHER EXPERIENCE

- Martial arts practitioner (Aikido, Judo), since 2010.
- Rock climbing, hiking, and other outdoor activities.
- Chess player and assistant coach, 1997-2007.
- Cross country running, tennis, football and several other team sports.

# PRESENTATIONS AND PUBLICATIONS

#### PRESENTATIONS

- Oral presentations in 5 international conferences since 2011.
- Poster presentation in 3 international conferences since 2011.
- Constant oral presentations during group meetings.

#### PUBLICATIONS IN PEER-REVIEWED INTERNATIONAL JOURNALS

- 16 publications in international journals including Nano letters, ACS nano, Journal of the American Chemical Society, Scientific Reposts, etc, being cited more than 250 times since 2013 and having a h-index of 9.
- Full publication list can be found at: <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Rafael\_Camacho2">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Rafael\_Camacho2</a>

#### WEBSITE

More information about my research and teaching activities can be found at: <a href="https://camachodejay.github.io/">https://camachodejay.github.io/</a>